all right
[Music]
many health benefits have been
attributed to having higher vitamin D
levels in the blood examples include
reduced risk of musculoskeletal
disorders infectious diseases autoimmune
diseases cardiovascular disease diabetes
several types of cancer neural cognitive
dysfunction adverse pregnancy and birth
outcomes in all cause mortality but most
such attributions are based on
observational studies meaning just
drawing correlations between the two and
having high vitamin D levels may just be
a marker of good health and after all
vitamin D is the sunshine vitamin who
has higher levels of vitamin D in their
blood people who run around outside so
maybe the D is just a marker for
exercise and that's really what's
lowering disease risk and indeed when
Vitamin D supplements are actually put
to the test and randomized controlled
trials they often fail to support a
direct vitamin D benefit
in this video I'm going to explore the
randomized controlled trial data on
vitamin D supplementation for COPD
chronic obstructive pulmonary diseases
like emphysema critical illness like
whether we should be giving vitamin D to
people in the ICU cardiovascular disease
like heart attacks and strokes
preventing depression treating
depression vitamin D for weight loss and
vitamin D for lung cancer survival
prostate cancer survival and colorectal
cancer survival what do you think do you
think Vitamin D supplements will help
with some of them all of them none of
them let's find out the efficacy of
vitamin D therapy for patients with COPD
a meta-analysis of randomized controlled
trials found that compared to Placebo
vitamin D can improve lung function
improve six minute walk distance and
reduce acute exacerbation sputum volume
and COPD assessment test scores in other
words so far so good Vitamin D
supplements are effective for treating
COPD
what about vitamin D supplementation for
critically ill adult patients if your
loved one ends up in the ICU for
whatever reason should you try to press
the doctors to give them a vitamin D
boost overall nine randomized controlled
trials involving nearly 2 000 patients
were included and
no significant difference in mortality
was observed
okay so so far D is one for two what
about cardiovascular disease widespread
fascination with vitamin D is a Panacea
is responsible for nearly a hundred-fold
increase in vitamin D testing and
supplementation over the last decade and
no wonder follow people over time and
there is an unequivocal association
between low vitamin D status and
people's risk of getting and dying from
our leading killer cardiovascular
disease but is it cause and effect maybe
low vitamin D levels are a result of
cardiovascular disease rather than the
cause if you have chest pain you're
probably not out in the sun running
around that's why there's been more than
20 randomized control trials to put
vitamin D to the test and no benefit for
heart attacks no benefit for strokes no
benefit for mortality
the good news of course is that heart
disease is preventable is reversible but
requires significant cleaning up of your
diet
what about vitamin D for preventing
depression among older adults five years
of vitamin D supplementation had no
effect on the occurrence of depression
or change in mood scores these findings
do not support the use of D to prevent
depression what about treating
depression every single one of the
trials for patients suffering from major
depression found a benefit to vitamin D
supplementation over Placebo though more
is not necessarily better and it may
take a few months for it to kick in
let's see how we're doing on the
scoreboard
obesity is next effects of vitamin D
supplementation on General and abdominal
obesity results from 20 randomized
controlled trials show no significant
effect on the measures of obesity
including BMI weight circumference or
waist to height ratio
treating cancer is up next vitamin D
supplementation and survival of patients
with the most common type of lung cancer
in early stage lung cancer all you can
do is try cutting out the primary tumor
but despite adding chemo tumor relapse
rates remain high surgeons noted that
patients who had surgery during the
summer seem to do better than those in
the winter which was chalked up to
higher vitamin D status so they
randomized patients to 1200
international units of vitamin D A day
or Placebo and over the next few years
no significant difference in either
relapse free survival or overall
survival was seen with vitamin D
compared with the placebo group
that was in the total study population
what if you just looked at the patients
who started out with low vitamin D
levels in that case there did appear to
be a benefit from D supplementation
among those starting out with D levels
under 20 nanograms per milliliter which
is equivalent to 50 nanomoles per liter
depends which units your lab uses half
of those who took the placebo relapsed
and have died but those who started out
with low levels and were treated with
actual vitamin D 86 percent remained in
remission and 91 percent remained alive
what about the effects of vitamin D
supplementation on prostate cancer a
systematic review a meta-analysis of
clinical trials found that there were no
significant differences in total
mortality between participants receiving
vitamin D supplementation and those
receiving placebo
that brings us to here though again note
the lung cancer benefit was only seen in
those who started out with low levels
and vitamin D supplementation for
colorectal cancer survival yes a
systematic review on meta-analysis
randomized controlled trials found that
supplementation imparts a 30 reduction
in bad outcomes overall with a 24
reduction in the risk of dying
specifically from your colorectal cancer
and a third lower risk of disease
progression or death from any cause the
optimal dose for this survival benefit
remains unclear since the trials use
different doses but it looks like
between two thousand and four thousand
international units a day is a good
place to start
foreign